<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>In the county of palatine in Durham, near Ferry-Hill, Jan. 25. 1682. Was acted the most horrid and barbarous murder that ever was heard on in the north or elsewhere, upon the bodies of John Brasse, Jane Brasse, and Elizabeth Brasse, while their parents were gone to Ferry-Hill, not half a mile from there own home. As may be seen by this following relation ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614711</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03773)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2755:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>In the county of palatine in Durham, near Ferry-Hill, Jan. 25. 1682. Was acted the most horrid and barbarous murder that ever was heard on in the north or elsewhere, upon the bodies of John Brasse, Jane Brasse, and Elizabeth Brasse, while their parents were gone to Ferry-Hill, not half a mile from there own home. As may be seen by this following relation ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. M. and sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Murder --  England --  Durham --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>
               <hi>In the County of PALATINE IN DURHAM, NEAR FERRY-HILL,</hi> 
               <date>
                  <hi>Jan. 25th. 1682.</hi>
               </date> Was Acted the moſt Horrid and Barbarous Murder that ever was heard on in the <hi>North</hi> or elſewhere, upon the Bodies of <hi>John Braſſe, Jane Braſſe,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Braſſe,</hi> while their Parents were gone to <hi>Ferry-Hill,</hi> not half a Mile from there own Home. As may be ſeen by this following Relation</head>
            <p>ON <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 25th. of the <hi>January,</hi> 1682. being St. <hi>Pauls</hi> day, <hi>John Braſſe</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> his Wife, going that Evening to <hi>Ferry-Hill</hi> (a Town not half a Mile diſtant from their own Houſe) they left <hi>John</hi> their Son, Aged <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen</hi> years; <hi>Jane,</hi> their daughter about <hi>Nineteen</hi> years of Age; and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> their Daughter, being <hi>Ten</hi> years of Age. All three were hopeful Children, and well Educated. Theſe three young People being left at Home, with one <hi>Andrew Mills</hi> their Servant: About <hi>Nine</hi> of the Clock the ſame Night, this <hi>Andrew Mills</hi> came to the Houſe where his Maſter and Dame were at <hi>Ferry-Hill,</hi> to Acquaint them with this ſad News, ſaying, Dame, our <hi>Johnny</hi> and <hi>Jany</hi> are both Kill'd. The Mother crying out, Asked what was become of her Little One. This <hi>Andrew Mills,</hi> Anſwered, and ſaid, there were two Men in the Houſe, whilſt he was feeding the Oxen, and he heard one ſay to the other, <hi>Kill All, Kill All.</hi> But the Mother Reply'd, Villain, none but thou has Murther'd my Children.</p>
            <p>Upon this, People of all Sorts in abundance flocked to the Houſe, (taking the ſaid <hi>Andrew Mills</hi> along with them) where they found all the three Perſons moſt Barbarouſly and Inhumanely Murther'd: Their Throats being Cut, their Bodys great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mangled, eſpecially their Heads and Necks. Two <hi>Axes</hi> was found on the Floor all Bloody, both Heads and Handles. This <hi>Mills,</hi> was ſuſpected by all to be the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and being ſearched, found in his <hi>Pocket,</hi> his <hi>Knife</hi> all Bloudy, but denied the Fact.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Coroner</hi> being ſent for, and calling a <hi>Jury,</hi> Impanell'd them; they Examined the <hi>Rogue,</hi> who denies all. Whereupon the <hi>Coroner</hi> adviſing the <hi>Jury</hi> to withdraw, Examins the <hi>Fellow</hi> alone, telling him (if he were guilty) and did confeſs the Fact, he would befriend him in ſaving his Life. Upon this, the <hi>Villain</hi> confeſt he did it. Saying, whilſt the two Eldeſt were aſleep (but not in Bed) he Kill'd them both. And afterwards, took the Little one out of its Bed and Murthered that alſo. He ſaid, after he had ſo done, he left them all in one Room. In his confeſſion he further faith, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended but Four dayes before to have Murdred the whole Family, but wanted opportunity.</p>
            <p>What might be the Cauſe for theſe Horible Murrders, is not yet known, he living there but a ſhort time, and no differences in the Family.</p>
            <p>Who ever doubts the Truth of this, may be further ſatisfied by Mr. <hi>Samuel Newton</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Gray-Fryers,</hi> whom this Relation was ſent to, and does know the Parents of the Murdred-Children, and did know the Children likewiſe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. M.</hi> and ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
